I've always loved CTFs! Not only are they a
fantastic learning resource, but also they give
me the feeling of competitiveness that I miss
from the days when I played football. However,
I didn't play CTFs much in the last few years
so I decided to change that. I've reached out
to my friends from JustCatTheFish team -
TOP 12 in the world on CTFtime last year.
I played with members of this team a few years
ago. Now, they invited me to play 0CTF with them.
I knew that tasks on real CTFs are really hard but
I still didn't appreciate them enough. Especially
that this CTF had maximum weight on CTFtime.org
world ranking which means it should also be
adequately difficult compared to other CTFs.
During the CTF, I struggled a lot but honestly,
one of the reasons I'm here is to make mistakes
and learn from other people. Because people in
this team are extremely skilled hackers and
I can learn so much from them! In this video,
I will show you how we solved the 'where are you
from?' task which involved two CVEs: AJP request
smuggling and the Ghostcat vulnerability.
Enjoy! For the task, we had an Apache httpd
as a front-end server and Apache Tomcat as a
backend and we had no access to the source code.
There was no real functionality - the server
only responded with some internal IP address
which we didn't know what it meant. And the
name of the task, plus having our own instance,
suggested a bug like request smuggling,
some kind of desync, maybe an SSRF.
From server headers, we could judge versions
of httpd and Tomcat. The front-end server was
2.4.53 which was only one from latest version
which I initially ignored. Tomcat, however,
was version 9.0.30 which was from 2020. And I
saw that it is vulnerable to potential remote
code execution via AJP protocol. And I immediately
connected the dots that I saw the vulnerability in
httpd about request smuggling, also in the AJP
which, at that point, I didn't know what it was.
AJP stands for Apache JServ Protocol and it
is a binary protocol which is used between
these two servers to communicate
instead of using an HTTP protocol.
For example, instead of wasting 12 bytes in
every single request for the Content-Type header,
there is a two-byte sequence that indicates
this header and so on, and so on...
So when I send GET to the front-end server, it
translates this HTTP request into an AJP packet.
One request - one packet, nothing interesting.
The format of the packet looks like this. First,
there are two magic bytes 0x12 0x34. Next, there
is the length of the whole AJP packet. Then,
there's a byte that says the type of the
packet. In our case it will always be 0x02
which means forward request packet. Then,
the next one will indicate the HTTP method.
The GET is indicated by code 2 and POST is 4.
Then, there's some data about the request like
the host, the request URI, then there are headers
and finally, there are some additional parameters.
And that's what happens when we send a GET request
without the body. But what happens when we send
a POST? It gets a bit more interesting because
the body of our request is sent separately from
the headers. So we have one HTTP request but two
AJP packets. And that's a good start if you are
looking for request smuggling. Our goal is to
split these two packets so that Tomcat treats
the body of our request as a new request. It's
because the AJP protocol in itself gives us a lot
of power and in this particular case, we need
it to exploit arbitrary file read on Tomcat.
In the packet with headers, there are magic
bytes, then there is the length of the packet
and then there is type of the packet and type
of the HTTP method. And I would think that the
request body would look similarly. I would expect
magic bytes as well, I would expect a packet
length and then I would expect some kind of byte
indicating that this packet is a request body.
But it's not the case. Turns out that in request
body, there is no packet type at all and the
packet length is followed by the data length
which, in all packets I've noticed, was just
packet length -2. And then, there's your whole
body which is forwarded without any modifications.
I didn't read the docs as meticulously when I
was solving the challenge but when preparing
for this video, I saw that even the docs say that
"this seems like a mistake". Because how does the
Tomcat know if this AJP packet is a request body
with length 514 or is it a GET forward request?
Tomcat looks at the previous packet. If
it contained the Content-Length header,
Tomcat treats the next one as its body. So
every time any AJP packet arrives to Tomcat,
it asks a question: did the previous
packet contain a Content-Length header?
If it didn't, the current packet is a brand new
request. If it did, the current packet is a body.
So if you could trick httpd to send your
body of the request in a situation where the
previous packet would not have the Content-Length
header, you would have the AJP request smuggling.
But how do you do this? If you don't
send the Content-Length header at all,
you GET 400 Bad Request and you're not even
talking with Tomcat. The next idea you might
have is to send Transfer-Encoding: chunked header.
However, when that happens Apache httpd doesn't
send the body at all. I didn't find any piece of
the documentation that would explain this behavior
but the comment in the source code says that
"the AJP protocol does not want body data yet".
How about an invalid Transfer-Encoding header?
When you do this, you also get 400 Bad Request.
But when you send Transfer-Encoding: chunked,
chunked, it's valid enough that you don't GET
400 Bad Request but it's also not equal to
string "chunked" which would make httpd get
inside the if that would not send the body. So
when you do this, it forwards the request with
this header and then sends your body in the
next AJP packet. And what does the Tomcat do
with the Transfer-Encoding header? I looked at
the source code of Tomcat and it doesn't even
mention the Transfer-Encoding header so I think
it doesn't do anything with it. All Tomcat
does when it sees our body is asking itself
a question: did the previous request contain
a Content-Length header? And in this case it
didn't so our body is processed as a new request.
And this is the first half of the task which
is CVE-2022-26377 AJP request smuggling in
Apache httpd. And I was reading the analysis of
this vulnerability in a Chinese blogpost and,
of course, back then, nothing was as clear to
me as it is now. And there was a payload in this
blogpost but I didn't know what it was doing. To
understand it, I created a simple python script
to parse the AJP message which I then extended
by the ability to create my own AJP messages.
The trick is to make the body of our request
exactly 514 bytes long. Why? Because, after
being hex encoded, it is 0x0202. And these bytes
are prepended by httpd to our request. These two
packets are forwarded to Tomcat. The first one is
processed without any problems - it's a normal AJP
packet without the Content-Length header. Then,
the second packet is processed by Tomcat - the
request body. Tomcat asks the question did
the previous packet contain a Content-Length
header and in this case it didn't because it
contained Transfer-Encoding: chunked, chunked
so Tomcat does not treat this as a request
body. On bytes 4 and 5, there is the length
of the packet but now Tomcat processes it as a new
request. It decodes it as forward request method
and in this case GET HTTP method. And the rest of
our packet must look like a valid AJP packet which
gives us possibility to send requests anywhere
and further exploit the second vulnerability.
And now it's time to exploit Tomcat.
It's a vulnerability where you can use
request attributes within an AJP packet
that override what you are requesting.
So in the original request URI, you said that you
want to request index.jsp which, of course, is
perfectly fine. But then, in the attributes, you
override this and you say you've changed your mind
and you wanted to request the web.xml instead.
This file often contains Tomcat credentials.
And, of course, you can read any other
file that can give you something. However,
when solving the challenge, we couldn't get
any file read for a long time. The problem was
that this was very random - you send a POST with
your smuggled AJP packet but the response to it
is returned in one of the future responses. And
it wasn't the next response or the second next.
It could be a few responses or it could even be
a few tens of responses further. And I wasted
hours here because I didn't account for that and
I didn't understand why the same things sometimes
work and other times they don't. And initially,
I saw the good error - the error that showed me
that the server tried to read the web.xml
file but it didn't work and then for hours,
I couldn't replicate getting the same error. At
this point, I left the task to my teammates and
I went on to check another one. In hindsight,
it was my mistake because I was very close to
solving this challenge but had I been doing
it alone I probably would not solve it.
Later, our solution to this problem was sending
only one POST request with a payload and then
sending multiple GETs in an infinite loop until we
would get a response to the smuggled AJP packet.
And the trick that was key to finally solving this
challenge had to do with JSP files. They look like
this - kinda like templates. And when you request
this file, you usually will get the rendered
version. However, when your original request URI
in the AJP packet is not JSP but whatever else
and then in your attributes you,
override this to get the index.jsp,
then the JSP file is not rendered but instead, you
see the whole content. Inside the index.jsp file,
there was just an if that checked the remote
address which had to be equal to a hard-coded one.
It was not a problem because it's one of the
fields from the AJP packet which we had full
control over. This is the final packet that my
teammate sent which gave him the flag. We were
one of the 10 teams to solve the challenge
and we ended the CTF at strong fifth place.
Thank you for watching this video! If you
want to check another write-up from CTF,
check out this one where I solve the challenge
created by LiveOverflow. For now,
thank you for watching and goodbye!